A Guide to the Thomas H. Hunter Collection 1934-1995
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library
- HUNTER ADDITION
  - 1990 - HARVARD SCHOOL OF MEDICINE 1990, TLS, TD, ALS, CERTIFICATE, AN, MEMORABILIA (Box-folder 14-01)
    HARVARD SCHOOL OF MEDICINE REPORT WITH ARTICLE ON THOMAS H. HUNTER, DONORS FOR THOMAS H. HUNTER PROFESSORSHIP
  - VIGNETTE OCT 1990, TD (Box-folder 14-02)
    ABORTION - THOMAS H. HUNTER THOUGHTS ON
  - 1991 CORRESPONDENCE 1991, TLS, TL, TN, AN, TD, MISC. (Box-folder 14-03)
    LETTER NEVER SENT TO CHARLES KURALT ABOUT EXPERIENCE IN COLUMBIA
  - THOMAS H. HUNTER PAPERS MISCELLANEOUS 1980-1991 (?), TD, TLS, AN (Box-folder 14-04)
    STATISTICS IN CLINICAL MEDICINE, COMMUNICATIONS GAP IN BIOMEDICAL ETHICS
  - MEDICAL ETHICS COMMITTEE - UVA OCT 1983-1991, TD (Box-folder 14-05)
    UVA MEDICAL ETHICS
  - UVA CENTER FOR BIOMEDICAL ETHICS 1992-1994, TD, MEMORABILIA (Box-folder 14-07)
  - 1993 - MEDICAL CENTER HOUR 1993, TLS, TD, PHOTO, AD (Box-folder 14-08)
    MEDICAL CENTER HOUR NOTES - ANNIE LIPSCOMB LECTURE, THE GOOD OLD DAYS: HOW GOOD WERE THEY?; O'KANE DRAWING OF THOMAS H. HUNTER
  - 50TH ANNIVERSARY 1993, DRAWING, CARD, ALS, TLS, ANS, POEM (Box-folder 14-09)
    THOMAS H. HUNTER/ANNE HUNTER 50TH ANNIVERSARY
  - THE WAY WE DIE 1993-1995, TLS, MEMORABILIA (Box-folder 14-10)
    THE WAY WE DIE--FILM PROJECT
  - 1994-MENTORS 1994, AD, PHOTO (Box-folder 14-11)
    THOMAS H. HUNTER'S DESCRIPTION OF HIS MENTORS
  - MEDICAL CLASS - PLAY PROGRAMS 1981-1989, MEMORABILIA (Box-folder 14-12)
    MEDICAL CLASS PLAY PROGRAMS 1980S
  - THOMAS H. HUNTER CHAIR IN INTERNATIONAL MEDICINE 198?, TD (Box-folder 14-13)
  - CHRISTMAS CARDS FROM KOREA MISC., CHRISTMAS CARDS (Box-folder 14-14)
  - CHIRSTMAS CARDS MISC., CHRISTMAS CARDS (Box-folder 14-15)
  - OLD THERAPY DOCUMENTS 1950S-60S, TD, PHOTO (Box-folder 14-16)
  - THOMAS H. HUNTER MEMORIAL SERVICE PROGRAMS 30 October 1997, 2 programs (Box-folder 14-17)
    THOMAS H. HUNTER DIED 23 OCTOBER 1997
  - PENCIL SKETCH OF MEDICAL SCHOOL BUILDING, BY DON SWANN; SIGNED BY COLLEAGUES OF THOMAS H. HUNTER June 30, 1981, AMS (Box-folder shelf-P4)
    THOMAS H. HUNTER, M. D., PROFESSOR OF MEDICINE, FEB. 1, 1953-JUNE 30, 1981
  - BELMONT HILL SCHOOL - CUM LAUDE MAY 1931, MEMORABILIA/CERTIFICATE (Box-folder UNBOX-)
    BELMONT HILL SCHOOL CUM LAUDE CERTIFICATE
- The life and times of Thomas H. Hunter, circa 1993-1997 August 18
  These videos document a series of interviews with Dr. Thomas H. Hunter conducted by Dr. Edward W. Hook. The subject matter is biographical, with special emphasis on Dr. Hunter's experiences as Dean of the University of Virginia School of Medicine, Chancellor of Medical affairs, and Owen R. Cheatham Professor of Science.
  - Birth to seven years of age, undated., Part 1; 1 master videocassette, 1 preservation DVD (Box-folder 15)
    Hunter describes parents, grandparents, uncles, parents’ divorce, transportation of that era, family finances, and his childhood before polio.
  - Childhood after polio, 1993 July 6, Part 2; 1 master videocassette, 1 preservation DVD (Box-folder 15)
    Hunter describes effects of polio; living with his mother in Boston while receiving treatment; remarriage of mother; spending summers in Niles, Michigan; school years; classmates that became life-long friends; participating on the rowing team; not being considered "a cripple.”
  - Childhood and family life, 1993 July 26, Part 3; 1 master videocassette, 1 preservation DVD (Box-folder 15)
    Hunter describes "no books, no God"; superstition about the number 13; polio and the possible cause; polio treatment; career choices; father, mother, grandfathers, and Aunt Jesse; summers in Niles, Michigan; schools, headmasters and classmates; importance of participating on rowing team despite being disabled in that era.
    Video concludes with Photographs of family, friends and Dr. Hunter at various ages. Images show: Grandfather Hunter; Florence (Patchen) Hunter, grandmother; father in office, the early years before marriage; father smoking a pipe in front of a mirror; Aunt Jesse (devoted herself to 4 generations of Hunter men, never married, and lived with Dr. Hunter until her death); Hunter's mother and him as an infant; Uncle on mother's side; Hunter as an infant; Hunter and mother at approximate age of 2 l/2 - 3 years old; Hunter in wagon, about 3 years old; Barron Lake with grandfather and Aunt Jesse; Hunter on tricycle, about 4 years old; Hunter working with grandfather on farm in Niles, Michigan, about 5-6 years old; Hunter with father at about 5; Hunter with wagon and horse, which belonged to the neighbor; Uncle LeMont, father, and Hunter, first year after polio in 1922 at Barron Lake house; Hunter on crutches at the Niles, Michigan home; Class of Belmont Hill, Boston; Mother at a much later date; Hunter 9 - 11 years old; Hunter, 21 years old, an undergraduate at Harvard, about 1934.
  - The Belmont School era, 1993 July 29, Part 4; 1 master videocassette, 1 preservation DVD (Box-folder 15)
    Hunter describes his years at Bellmont Hill School, Boston, as the formative days of his childhood. He is very thankful for the time, events, and people of these years at this school; thought of headmasters and friends as his family; was a Monday thru Friday boarder and home on weekends; participated in rowing, tennis, golf and the football team; won prizes in French and Latin and the School Medal; learned the value of team effort; became aware of his polio and its residual damage, but accepted it and incorporated it into his life.
  - The Harvard years, 1931-1935, 1993 August 9, Part 5; 1 master videocassette, 1 preservation DVD (Box-folder 15)
    Hunter describes majoring in Psychology and Philosophy; financing his education through scholarships and employment; the pros and cons of Harvard University; his experiences on the honors bracket, student council, as officer of the class, as member of the Signet Society, and playing golf; his favorite courses in the fine arts.
  - The Cambridge years, 1935, 1993 August 12, Part 6; 1 master videocassette, 1 preservation DVD (Box-folder 15)
    Hunter graduated from Harvard and traveled by sea to England; was assigned a room at the Inner Court of Trinity Hall; received the Henry Fellowship for 1 year; stayed at Cambridge for 3 years; was coxswain on the rowing team; received the Henry Fellowship his second year; continued rowing in year three and received his "blue" (letter) on the varsity team; studied and worked all year with no exams; completed oral examinations for a week at the end of the year.
  - The Cambridge years, 1938-1940, 1993 August 18, Part 7; 1 master videocassette, 1 preservation DVD (Box-folder 15)
    Hunter prepared for studying medicine at Harvard. Courses of study included anatomy, biochemistry, physiology, pharmacology, pathology, and organic chemistry. Students were assigned a tutor who oversaw the college, economic, and cultural life of the student. Hunter departed from Cambridge in 1938; was "very obtuse to the menace of Hitler and war and never got the full impact of the war" until much later; returned to Harvard to pursue medical education fall, 1938.
  - Harvard Medical School, 1941-1944, 1993 October 7, Part 8; 1 master videocassette, 1 preservation DVD (Box-folder 15)
    Hunter started Harvard Medical School fall, 1938 and graduated 1940; satisfied basic science requirements, but had limited clinical experience; had Dr. Stead, as instructor at the Boston City Hospital; rotated between 3 different hospitals; did surgical rotation at Brigham Young; worked with Dr. Gamble in the lab (this was his first move into research and lab work); co-authored a paper with Dr. Alfred Shoal on the development and method for measuring serum protein; began internship at the Presbyterian Hospital in New York, February, 1941; married in 1943.
  - Early years after graduation and the impact of WWII, 1940-1945, 1993 November 9, Part 9; 1 master videocassette, 1 preservation DVD (Box-folder 15)
    Hunter graduated in 1940; completed internship, 1941-1944; completed residency in 1945. Dr. William Parson, Professor Emeritus, University of Virginia and Chairman of the Department of Medicine 1949-1966 joins Dr. Hunter and Dr. Hook in part 9. Both had interned at Presbyterian Hospital in New York. Parson was one year ahead of Hunter. Hunter was a “pup” for 3 months which involved doing procedures, testing, and lab work from the periphery. After 3 months Hunter rotated to surgery, took care of patients, did private service, worked on female and male wards. After attack on Pearl Harbor everyone went off to war. Hunter remained in the United States; married on March 7, 1943; completed residency in 1945; attended the Army Medical School, Walter Reed Hospital, and studied tropical medicine; travelled to Cost Rica where he observed poor patient care which impacted him deeply; became instructor in medicine at the College of Physicians and Surgery at Columbia University; worked with penicillin in the early days of development and manufacture; participated in human research; wrestled with ethical decisions regarding informed consent of the patient.
  - Recruitment and experiences as Dean of University of Virginia School of Medicine, 1993 November 11, Part 10; 1 master videocassette, 1 preservation DVD (Box-folder 15)
    Hunter quickly assumed higher position and responsibilities at Columbia; received intense clinical experience during this time; described how Dr. Parson was instrumental in bringing Dr. Hunter to U.Va. as Chairman of Internal Medicine; visited UVA in 1952 and was impressed but still did not want the job; was re-invited to U.Va. to be the Dean; as Dean, built relationships with universities, medical schools, and the NIH; through relationship with the NIH and Ken Crispell, contributed to the expansion of the basic sciences buildings; regretted resisting expansion and fund raising during his years as dean; experienced hostility when he signed a document and agreed with Medicare during the Kennedy administration; traveled to South America to work and he was ousted from the deanship while away; became Chancellor in 1964; regretted not anticipating or respecting the roles of African-Americans and women in medicine, education, and leadership; worked to keep the medical school an integral part of the university.
  - Private practice, travel to South America, and Assistant Dean at Washington University, 1945-1952, 1993 November 16, Part 11; 1 master videocassette, 1 preservation DVD (Box-folder 15)
    Hunter earned a $2500.00 salary after finishing residency in 1947; decided he could not stay at the hospital; entered private practice where first annual salary was $13,000.00; traveled to South America for 6 weeks; worked in the United Fruit Company hospital where most patients were employees with various diseases and conditions; remained an instructor at Columbia, studying, investigating, and treating patients with penicillin from Pfizer; taught many nursing students; was contacted by Washington University in 1947; moved to Washington University in St. Louis in 1947 with wife, 2 children, elderly aunt and a maid; attended on the ward with no private practice; had his own lab where he could continue his work with penicillin; was promoted to Associate Professor of Medicine and Associate Dean; uncovered the synergy between penicillin and streptomycin (this discovery occurred while treating a patient).
  - Dean of the University of Virginia School of Medicine 1952-1953, 1993 November 30, Part 12; 1 master videocassette, 1 preservation DVD (Box-folder 15)
    Hunter was invited by Dr. Parsons in 1952 for job as the Dean of Medicine; though the School of Medicine was very small and poor, but had an excellent reputation for turning out reputable graduates. Hunter found the budget situation impossible to work with; was invited back to U.Va. after all candidates had been interviewed. Colgate Darden was the current president and was persuasive in convincing Hunter to come to U.Va. Hunter was attracted by the fact that the University was an old school with great assets. He viewed U.Va. as a relatively small, manageable, high quality academic setting not requiring a big administrative machine. Hunter’s agenda included gaining financial support from the State Assembly, turning out more graduates on a slightly larger scale, accepting the cream-of-the-crop applicants, and providing better jobs and training. Hunter’s first years were spent working with students, teaching, and being with patients. He did not come to U.Va. with aggressive ideas for building and growth.
    Some distortion in tape.
  - Dean of the University of Virginia School of Medicine, 1993 December 14, Part 13; 1 master videocassette, 1 preservation DVD (Box-folder 15)
    Hunter arrived as Dean February, 1953; was 40 years old; had to work with an impossible budget; recieved a low salary; reported to the President of the University; was moved by the degree of growth and quality of the University; saw that there was a lot to be accomplished. There was a faculty of about 50-60 people and 76 students; almost all male; almost all white; from a wide geographic distribution. Hunter worked to break down the negative attitude of potential faculty recruits who saw U.Va. as poor, small, restricted, and provincial; agitated some because he did not want to build buildings, but build people; had a small lab in McKim and a grant during his first 7-10 years; worked on the chemical mechanism of penicillin on different states of organisms and antibacterial activities in other places and its effects in water, plants, and foreign bodies. Hunter's interests declined in the lab, and he became more excited by teaching. He focused on NIH, AAMC, international affairs, and ethics. This took him outside the University and has been attributed to putting the School of Medicine on the map. Hunter also had difficulties in the early years regarding racism and his “color blindness,” the Rose Garden affair (Medicare), and a speech he gave to a national gathering of pharmacologists blasting McCarthy.
  - Dean of the University of Virginia School of Medicine, 1953-1965, 1993 December 16, Part 14; 1 master videocassette, 1 preservation DVD (Box-folder 15)
    Hunter’s strongest supporters during this period were Dr. Parsons, Doug Eastwood, and Dave Smith. Hunter felt that the Dean had to balance obligation to the university and the department; emphasized a cooperative environment at the School of Medicine where people were comfortable together; did not realize how inadequate many of the facilities were and how the financial structure needed a boost from various sources; credits Ken Crispell with the vision that moved the School forward (Crispell obtained grants to construct buildings for the basic sciences); during this time was president of AAMC, served a 6 year tour at Harvard Board of Overseers, and worked with the NIH International Committee; conceded that his outside interests took up a lot of his time from the University; spent 1962-1963 in California and Colombia; became Chancellor for Medical Affairs in 1966; served as a member of the Center for Advanced Study; was involved with the Rose Garden Affair (Medicare).
  - California and Colombia, 1962-1963, 1994 February 3, Part 15; 1 master videocassette, 1 preservation DVD (Box-folder 15)
    Hunter temporarily re-located because of the reaction to his support of Medicare (the Rose Garden Affair); was invited by the Rockefeller Foundation and NIH to start a new international medical school program; relocated to California. The program sought to develop American-style medical schools abroad in key areas. Hunter describes the difficulties of implementing the program in Colombia; outlines reasons for its failure. Spring, 1963, Hunter suffered a collapsed lung and underwent surgery. Complications occurred and he was sent to Presbyterian Hospital in New York. Fall, 1963, Hunter, still recovering, returned to U.Va. and stepped down to become Chancellor of Medical Affairs.
  - Stepping down as Dean of University of Virginia School of Medicine, 1963-1971, 1994 February 10, Part 16; 1 master videocassette, 1 preservation DVD (Box-folder 15)
    Hunter discusses the separation of the School of Public Health and the School of Medicine; discusses reasons for his stepping down as Dean of the School of Medicine; became Chancellor of Medical Affairs (title was later changed to Vice President of Health Affairs with no change in responsibilities); in 1971 named Owen R. Cheatham Professor of Science; no longer required to work in the framework of the administration.
    Tape is damaged at half-way point.
  - Retirement and further reflection, 1994 February 17, Part 17; 1 master videocassette, 1 preservation DVD (Box-folder 15)
    Hunter clarifies points from previous interviews and discusses future topics of conversation; gives views on retirement (retired in 1981 at the age of 68); felt that he should retire so as not to be a “financial drain” on the institution; realizes that his time at UVA was a period where many changes were taking place across the country and at UVA in school structures, requirements, and financial support; was a member of several prestigious societies: Center for Advanced Studies, speaker at a seminar at the Centennial Meeting Of the Massachusetts Department of Public Health, Chair of the University Wide Purpose Committee, Distinguished Service Member of AAMC, President of AAMC, UVA Senate, and a member of the American Academy of Arts and Sciences; was instrumental in starting several Medical Schools: Brown, Morehouse College; Tufts; was awarded the Thomas Jefferson Award and the Raven Society Award.
  - Clarification and miscellaneous topics, 1994 February 22, Part 18; 1 master videocassette, 1 preservation DVD (Box-folder 15)
    Dr. Hook clarifies date and content of the letter of resignation written by Hunter on March 24, 1964 to Dr. Edgar Shannon. It was understood that Dr. Ken Crispell, who had been serving in the position as Acting Dean would be appointed as Dean of the Medical School on the same day. Also on March 24, 1964 Shannon made Hunter Chancellor. Crispell wanted to tighten up the Medical School administration and Hunter wanted to “branch out” into various areas of the SChool of Medicine and University. Hunter wanted to explore the national and international aspects of medical education. Crispell sent Hunter a letter on April 3, 1964 outlining the concerns he had with vacant positions due to illness and positions vacated by faculty for various reasons. Hunter and Crispell worked together identifying and recruiting people for the various vacant positions in the basic sciences. Hook then investigates Hunter’s views on God, love, marriage, homosexuality, HIV/AIDS, and prostitution.
  - Recollections of deanship with Dr. Norman Thornton, 1994 February 24, Part 19; 1 master videocassette, 1 preservation DVD (Box-folder 15)
    Dr. Norman Thornton is interviewed with Hunter and recalls times when Hunter was Dean and Chancellor and the Rose Garden Affair. Thornton was a U.Va. undergraduate in 1926; graduated in 1936; served 4 years in the military; was associated with U.Va. as a student and faculty member for 29 years; gives gave his views and discusses Hunter’s years as Dean, sojourn to California, illness, return to dean after illness, resignation and appointment as chancellor; notes that since the beginning Hunter did not want administrative responsibilities. Hunter delegated to department heads; had an open door policy and provided help whenever he could, considering the poor budget; did not interfere with the department heads. Prominent figures in Hunter’s office were John Stacy, who was in charge of the hospital and Vincent Shay who was in charge of getting financial support for the institution. Vincent Archer and Hank Mulholland were responsible for all political aspects of getting money from Richmond. Ken Crispell is given credit for putting U.Va. on the map because of his promotion of the basic sciences and building expansions.
  - Recollections of deanship with Dr. John Harlan, 1994 March 7, Part 20; 1 master videocassette, 1 preservation DVD (Box-folder 15)
    Harlen was the administrative assistant when Hunter was Dean in 1953. Harlin verifies the history of Hunter as dean, chancellor, and Professor Emeritus; discusses the pressure from alumni to fire Hunter over his support of Medicare; states that Hunter was a born leader; discusses Hunter’s personnel interactions and budget management. The interview reviews the relationships of faculty, Dean, Vice President, and administrators at U.Va.; management styles; politics and economics; enormous changes of women rights and equality.
  - Recollections with Dr. Robert M. Berne, 1994 March 10, Part 21; 1 master videocassette, 1 preservation DVD (Box-folder 15)
    Interview with Dr. Robert M. Berne and Hunter. Berne was Chairman of the Physiology Department 1966-1988; Professor Emeritus in 1994; was recruited by Hunter to head the Physiology Department; was impressed by the new buildings, funding and grants available for renovations, and availability of new equipment and personnel. Most of Berne’s contact was with Ken Crispell. They discuss overall lack of funding in light of inflation, researcher salaries, and decline in support from the state.
  - Interview with Dr. Thomas Hunter, 1997 August 18, Part 22; 1 master videocassette, 1 preservation DVD (Box-folder 15)
    Dr. Hook and Dr. Leo S. Falk are with Dr. Hunter at his home in Cismont, VA. Dr. Hunter is in poor health, confined to his bed; is thankful for a fulfilling life; expresses a desire to be let “out of the trap he finds himself in”; reminisces and gives short bio of his life; cannot understand why people are delaying his death; has no interest in prolonging his existence; asks Dr. Hook to provide a morphine drip and let him peacefully slip away; discusses the topic of personal suicide, physician assisted suicide, and the legalities involved; asks Hook to “arrange for me to be allowed to have an appropriate exit.” Dr. Thomas Hunter died October 23, 1997.
  - Death and dying, undated, 1 master videocassette, 1 preservation DVD Jonathan Mednick, filmmaker;; Margot White, producer (Box-folder 15)
    Dr. Hook and Dr. Hunter discuss terminal illness and dying. Hunter has selected Hook to take care of medical decisions regarding his death when Hunter becomes incapable; does not want his wife to be burdened; discusses quality of life; emphasizes trust when selecting someone to make decisions regarding life support, resuscitation, withdrawing medications, etc.; felt that he was dying when he was in California; accepted it emotionally that he was dying; was not frightened by death. Hook and Hunter agree that patients with terminal illness are isolated. There should be care expanded to patients who know they do not have long to live. Today’s medicine is so advanced; prolongs the biological life as long as the vital processes are going on. Lawyers and others are taking over all decisions in many cases.
    Some portions of the tape have been deleted; cuts off abruptly at the end. Sticker on the outside of the VHS says Hilda Thomas.
  - Interview with Dr. Thomas Hunter, 1997 August 12, 1 videocassette, 1 preservation DVD (Box-folder 15)
    Interview with Dr. Hook and Hunter. Dr. Hunter is in poor health; discusses his quality of life and desire to be “allowed to die”; expresses feelings about Hook’s refusal to assist in suicide; discusses his legacy and how he wants to be remembered after death; shares thoughts about possible suicide of father and grandfather; expresses pride in his grandson. After the interview, Hook records his own thoughts about Hunter’s views on the topics of personal suicide and physician assisted suicide.